<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Annvix - Christianity</title><link href="https://annvix.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://annvix.com/feeds/christianity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://annvix.com/</id><updated>2016-09-11T14:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Consumer Christianity</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/consumer-christianity" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-11T14:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2016-09-11T14:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2016-09-11:/blog/consumer-christianity</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Image" src="https://annvix.com/images/food-man-person-eating.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we held a "Ministry Fair" at the church that serves to highlight the many ministries within our church as a way to highlight the sorts of things we do and also to allow others to volunteer and serve in particular areas where we have need.  As I stood at …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Image" src="https://annvix.com/images/food-man-person-eating.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we held a "Ministry Fair" at the church that serves to highlight the many ministries within our church as a way to highlight the sorts of things we do and also to allow others to volunteer and serve in particular areas where we have need.  As I stood at my station, I began to think about the church and why I, with my family, attend and serve... and it caused some interesting reflection that I wanted to share here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my firm belief that one of the biggest problems within the church today is that it has become an institution that seeks to change God for the sake of people, rather than to change people for the sake of God.  It has become "seeker friendly" and so much so that the gospel of Jesus Christ has been watered down to the point that it is indistinguishable from real Biblical truth.  It isn't hard to see... turn around and look at what many churches today preach, teach, and "sell" to people who come in the doors.  Instead of calling people to serve God, the church starts to serve the individual.  Instead of the church calling individuals to serve the body (which is the church and members of the Christian community, and also all mankind), it seeks to become more palatable to the masses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the words of Dietrich Bonhoffer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
"Cheap grace is the preaching of forgiveness without requiring repentance, baptism without church discipline, Communion without confession, absolution without personal confession. Cheap grace is grace without discipleship, grace without the cross, grace without Jesus Christ, living and incarnate."
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we get to this point?  The church used to be something that people gave their lives for (and, in many parts of the world, still do) but here in North America we equate the church to nothing more than a drive-through fast food joint.  We have become a McDonalds for the soul.  A Subway for the spirit.  To me, the obvious answer is that churches want more people, and I believe most have good intentions here.  The more folks who come through the doors, the more people who will have that encounter with Jesus and ultimately start down the road of relationship with Him that leads to eternal life.  Sure, some churches are thinking that more people mean more finances and they are financially driven although I don't think this is most churches (undoubtably there are more than a few that would fall into this kind of motivation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question I have for these churches that are willing to water down the message to get more people in the door is: what do you do with them once you have them?  If your lure to get people into the church is to preach messages about how much God loves you (He does) and how much He wants to bless you (He does), and how much it's all about &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; (it isn't really) then what do you do about the flip-side of the gospel that is just as important, if not more so?  If you spend all your time talking about these things and then toss in a message about repentance, about obedience, self-sacrifice, loving your neighbour like yourself, putting God first above all things... if you don't preach these things as part of the "whole package" then the people you brought in with the "it's all about you, baby" message will vote with their feet and walk because this new message isn't what drew them in to begin with.  So what are the chances these things will reach the pulpit?  Probably little chance because the fear will be that you've changed the menu and you've changed what they came for with something they need, but don't really want.  We can't be "bait and switch" churches because that doesn't work and deceives people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what are we left with?  Starting of as peddlers of cheap grace and staying that way.  Or we can preach a full gospel and stay true to it, showing integrity and honesty and deceiving no one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this is a real fear in a lot of churches today.  If they start preaching a &lt;i&gt;full&lt;/i&gt; gospel, who is going to stick around to hear it?  Sure some will, but for those who came to the church because it met &lt;i&gt;their&lt;/i&gt; needs, when those needs are no longer met, they'll leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the essence of consumer christianity.  Thomas C. Reeves, in his book &lt;i&gt;The Empty Church&lt;/i&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Christianity in modern America . . . tends to be easy, upbeat, convenient, and compatible. It does not require self-sacrifice, discipline, humility, an otherworldly outlook, a zeal for souls, a fear as well as love of God. There is little guilt and no punishment, and the payoff in heaven is virtually certain. What we now have might best be labeled ‘Consumer Christianity.’ The cost is low and customer satisfaction seems guaranteed.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn't the way the church was supposed to operate and as a Christian, this isn't how we're supposed to view the church.  There are two main points here:  the first is that the church has to stop catering to people and be what it was actually meant to be, what God designed it to be.  The second is that people have to stop looking at church as something that caters to their needs and making it all about their wants and desires.  I believe that if the second happens, the first will also.  But some churches just need to make the decision that, even if it means people leaving, they will preach a full gospel truth -- not watered down, not manipulated, and certainly not absent.  Why?  Because Jesus asked us to make disciples, not patrons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Christians, the church was not meant to serve our needs.  We were meant to serve the church, to be obedient to the call of God.  In Luke 9:23-34 (TLB), Jesus says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Then he said to all, “Anyone who wants to follow me must put aside his own desires and conveniences and carry his cross with him every day and keep close to me! Whoever loses his life for my sake will save it, but whoever insists on keeping his life will lose it;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to understand that sometimes we won't get what we want.  We need to understand that sometimes the pastor will preach a message that digs a little deep and makes us uncomfortable and that it isn't a license to leave to find somewhere else that preaches something a little softer.  We need to be ok with change and that sometimes people will rub us the wrong way and instead of looking for the exit, realize that we have a place here and maybe, just maybe, this is a good opportunity for growth.  The church is called the Body of Christ and we don't get to define what that looks like.  God calls us, and has designed us, to be a part of one body.  In 1 Corinthians 12 the Bible talks about the body and how we are necessary parts of it, and in Colossians 1:18a the Bible tells us that Jesus is the head of the body:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
He is the Head of the body made up of his people—that is, his Church—which he began
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we see that it's not up to us to determine whether or not we belong, whether or not we should leave, whether or not it meets our needs.  Instead, we need to know that we &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; belong, we should only leave if the Lord directs us elsewhere (after all, He places us where He wishes), and we need to start thinking about meeting the needs of others rather than just being in it for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife and I have been attending Christcity (started back when it was Bethesda Christian Fellowship) for about 18 years now.  We have seen pastors move on to other churches, we have seen many friends leave for a variety of reasons, and we have seen people who have remained loyal to that body of believers much longer than we have.  In fact, today we honoured the retirement of our Treasurer who has served faithfully for 46 years.  I can honestly say that remaining this long has not been without it's challenges!  Some of the people who have moved on have been very dear friends and it would have been so easy to leave with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except that my wife and I understood and acknowledged that God planted us in that church 18 years ago and we don't have the option of leaving until He says so.  This isn't about loyalty to one pastor, or even one building.  It's about loyalty to the God who said "this is where you belong" and understanding that God commands blessing when we remain in unity (Psalm 133).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so we have, and God has rewarded us immensely for remaining faithful to the place God has called us.  But even more than that, we don't come to the church as consumers, we come to the church as contributors.  When we come as contributors, yes, we consume, but we also take part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can easily be compared to the open source ecosystem.  There are many consumers of open source (in fact, a whole lot of what you use today, whether you realize it or not, is effectively consumed open source software, be it your phone, TV, router... heck, even your toaster).  There are, comparatively, few contributors.  And yet the contributors to open source will tell you, time and time again, that contributing to open source makes all the difference and there is great satisfaction to be had.  In fact, I'd say that open source contributors believe "it is better to give than to receive" because they know they will receive so much more than they contributed, because they are able to reap the fruit of the labours of others who, like themselves, contributed to something that was bigger than just "me".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what the church is meant to be.  We are meant to be partakers, to partner with God and the church He designed.  We are meant to serve.  We are meant to walk alongside our brothers and sisters in Christ.  We are meant to be active parts of the body.  And we are meant to be loyal and committed to the body, in the same way two people are committed in marriage.  I find the imagery of Christ and His Bride so potent because Jesus has made commitment to the church in the same way a husband does to his bride, and the church is meant to have that same level of commitment to her Husband.  And we, in turn, are meant to have the same level of commitment to both the Bride (church) as members of the body, and to the Husband (Jesus) as the Bride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll wrap this post up with Acts 20:28-35 (TLB) as a warning for both those who lead the church and for those who are a part of the church:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“And now beware! Be sure that you feed and shepherd God’s flock—his church, purchased with his blood—for the Holy Spirit is holding you responsible as overseers. I know full well that after I leave you, false teachers, like vicious wolves, will appear among you, not sparing the flock. Some of you yourselves will distort the truth in order to draw a following. Watch out! Remember the three years I was with you—my constant watchcare over you night and day and my many tears for you.

“And now I entrust you to God and his care and to his wonderful words that are able to build your faith and give you all the inheritance of those who are set apart for himself.

“I have never been hungry for money or fine clothing— you know that these hands of mine worked to pay my own way and even to supply the needs of those who were with me. And I was a constant example to you in helping the poor; for I remembered the words of the Lord Jesus, ‘It is more blessed to give than to receive.’”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category></entry><entry><title>Our Response to the Majesty of God</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/our-response-to-the-majesty-of-god" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-06-14T08:27:00-06:00</published><updated>2015-06-14T08:27:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2015-06-14:/blog/our-response-to-the-majesty-of-god</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is the transcript of what I spoke on at a Tuesday night at Christcity.  A few people missed it and wanted to know what I spoke about, so I'm sharing it here.  For those reading who may not "get it", this was delivered to Christians.  This isn't a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is the transcript of what I spoke on at a Tuesday night at Christcity.  A few people missed it and wanted to know what I spoke about, so I'm sharing it here.  For those reading who may not "get it", this was delivered to Christians.  This isn't a message to anyone else.  There are a lot of "Christians" out there who were told a lie: That becoming a Christian is all about reserving a seat in Heaven and having God do "stuff" for you.  That is part of it, absolutely, but that's not the main thrust (or even really a large part) of what Christianity is about.  That lie makes Christianity all about &lt;b&gt;you&lt;/b&gt; (a selfish thing) when the reality is Christianity is all about &lt;b&gt;Jesus Christ&lt;/b&gt; (a selfless thing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this really encourages Christians to continue walking the path that Jesus set before us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;May 5, 2015:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had initially wanted to speak about the awesome majesty of our God, as it is something that has been burning in my heart for months now.  I believe God wants us to fully understand the greatness of who our King is, and He has been speaking this to us, as a church, through recent sermons and the exhortations of people like Julia and Don in the past weeks.   I could certainly say much of the same tonight, but I want to speak about how we serve this majestic King and Lord, and how we express our love to Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bible says in John 14:15 (AMP):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“If you [really] love Me, you will keep (obey) My commands.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in John 14:21 (AMP):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“The person who has My commands and keeps them is the one who [really] loves Me; and whoever [really] loves Me will be loved by My Father, and I [too] will love him and will show (reveal, manifest) Myself to him. [I will let Myself be clearly seen by him and make Myself real to him.]”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question then becomes: do we love Him?  Because Jesus clearly says that there is exactly one expression of love towards Him: to obey His commandments.  Pop Christianity today would make God a common thing, one priority among many and that it’s ok to choose other things over God.  This can be in many areas of our lives: time, talent, and finances (or tithes).  Everything falls under these main areas.  Every day we have many options of how to prioritize our time, how and where we use our God-given abilities and talents, and what we spend our money on.  The world gives us many options on what to devote these things to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are important things to consider for three reasons.  The first is that it all comes down to directing them towards one of two people: do we use these things for our God, or for ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that these are all things given to us, and the Bible calls us stewards or managers of the things God has given us.  So if we believe these things are given to us, by God, and we are stewards of them, then they don’t belong to us and we are not owners but simply managers.  So I ask you: How is our stewardship?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, do we use these things in the light of Eternity, knowing that our existence on this planet is the blink of an eye or a drop in the ocean, and also keeping in mind that it is the only blink that counts and it is the single drop that defines what the rest of the ocean looks like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are sobering thoughts indeed.  We need to understand that it isn’t just what we say that matters.  God considers our words, our actions, and our motives.  All three need to line up.  The Bible has some very interesting things to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremiah 17:10 NLT-SE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“But I, the LORD, search all hearts and examine secret motives. I give all people their due rewards, according to what their actions deserve.””&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James 2:14–17 NLT-SE:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“What good is it, dear brothers and sisters, if you say you have faith but don’t show it by your actions? Can that kind of faith save anyone? Suppose you see a brother or sister who has no food or clothing, and you say, “Good-bye and have a good day; stay warm and eat well” —but then you don’t give that person any food or clothing. What good does that do? 
So you see, faith by itself isn’t enough. Unless it produces good deeds, it is dead and useless.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Titus 1:16 HCSB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“They profess to know God, but they deny Him by their works. They are detestable, disobedient, and disqualified for any good work.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 John 3:16–18 HCSB:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“This is how we have come to know love: He laid down His life for us. We should also lay down our lives for our brothers. If anyone has this world’s goods and sees his brother in need but closes his eyes to his need—how can God’s love reside in him?
Little children, we must not love with word or speech, but with truth and action.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just a sampling of what the Bible says about our actions and motives.  God demonstrated His love to us by His actions: He sent His only Son, who had existed with Him for eternity, to earth, to teach us and then bear the full weight of God’s wrath against sin, God’s wrath that belonged to each of us.  He interrupted a relationship that had existed for Eternity &lt;i&gt;before&lt;/i&gt; us, so that He could have a relationship in Eternity &lt;i&gt;with&lt;/i&gt; us.  God did this for you, and He did this for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we understand that God loves us this much, then it’s not too much of a stretch to suggest that we owe God a debt we can never repay.  The great thing is that we don’t have to repay it!  God did not set out a number of homeless people we needed to feed, or a number of people we needed to bring to church, or a number of times we needed to read the Bible.  He didn’t give us a set of rules to keep, He gave us a lifestyle to live and a Saviour to accept as our own and devote our entire being to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galatians 2:20 (NKJV) says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“I have been crucified with Christ; it is no longer I who live, but Christ lives in me; and the life which I now live in the flesh I live by faith in the Son of God, who loved me and gave Himself for me.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lifestyle includes loving God fully, which we’ve seen is demonstrated by keeping His commandments.  This is the lifestyle.  This new life we’ve received in Christ is not about us.  The old life, the sinful life, was about us.  This new life is all about Christ.  We are second to Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we believe this, if we believe the Bible, if we believe the Truth that the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of Truth, places into our hearts and haven’t hardened ourselves to Him, then we know that coming to church is not a chore, or a duty, or something common.  We have the privilege of being in the Presence of the King of kings!  The Uncreated God of the universe desires the privilege of spending time with us in His House!  Giving our tithes in a Biblical way is easy.  If we believe that we are stewards of that money and God has given it to us then we should never look at it as giving 10% back to God.  We should always look at it as God graciously giving us the 90% to do with as we want or need and that 10% returned is simply a way to tangibly demonstrate our gratitude and thankfulness for the rest, and our obedience to His commands.  Proper tithing proves our obedience to God and don’t think for a second that God doesn’t know how to count!  Giving less demonstrates that we still put ourselves first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If our time is likewise a gift from God, then we need to use it in a way that glorifies Him and advances eternity.  Do we show God gratitude for the time He has given us by “tithing” back our time and helping our “neighbour” (meaning everyone)?  Do we show God gratitude for the Church He has given to us and pour our time into it – not just for ourselves, but for others?  We need to realize that we don’t just come to church for our own benefit, but when we place ourselves here with a proper attitude of humility and reverence before God, He can use us to bless others around us.  And most importantly, when we come to church, we need to view it for what it really is: we are entering the Presence of Almighty God and ministering to Him.  Our praise, thanksgiving, worship, and prayers are our ministry before the Throne of God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I challenge you tonight to be like David and Isaiah, every day, and see what God does with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psalms 51:10 (NKJV) says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Create in me a clean heart, O God, And renew a steadfast spirit within me.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Isaiah 6:8 (NKJV) says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Also I heard the voice of the Lord, saying: “Whom shall I send, And who will go for Us?”   Then I said, “Here am I! Send me.””&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we have the courage to stand and say the same?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category></entry><entry><title>Bible Study 2014-11-16</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/bible-study-2014-11-16" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-19T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2014-11-19T20:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2014-11-19:/blog/bible-study-2014-11-16</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We've started a Bible study at the church so I'm going to just share some of the thoughts and scriptures that we look at each week.  This is our first week and the topic was &lt;i&gt;What does it mean to be a Christian?&lt;/i&gt;  The first thing we looked at was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We've started a Bible study at the church so I'm going to just share some of the thoughts and scriptures that we look at each week.  This is our first week and the topic was &lt;i&gt;What does it mean to be a Christian?&lt;/i&gt;  The first thing we looked at was the Apostles Creed and the Nicene Creed, both of which &lt;a href="http://linsec.ca/blog/2014/09/11/christian-statements-of-faith/"&gt;we've looked at here before&lt;/a&gt;.  I'm going to include the scripture we looked at and add emphasis to them, so when you see anything in bold those were the key phrases in the text we were looking at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Therefore, when many of His disciples heard this, they said, “&lt;b&gt;This teaching is hard!&lt;/b&gt; Who can accept it?”
Jesus, knowing in Himself that &lt;b&gt;His disciples&lt;/b&gt; were complaining about this, asked them, “&lt;b&gt;Does this offend you?&lt;/b&gt; Then what if you were to observe the Son of Man ascending to &lt;b&gt;where He was before&lt;/b&gt;? The Spirit is the One who gives life. The flesh doesn’t help at all. The words that I have spoken to you are spirit and are life. But there are some among you who don’t believe.” (For Jesus knew from the beginning those who would not believe and the one who would betray Him.) He said, “This is why I told you that no one can come to Me unless it is granted to him by the Father.”
&lt;b&gt;From that moment many of His disciples turned back and no longer accompanied Him&lt;/b&gt;. Therefore Jesus said to the Twelve, “You don’t want to go away too, do you?”
Simon Peter answered, “Lord, who will we go to? You have the words of eternal life. We have come to believe and know that You are the Holy One of God!””
(John 6:60–69 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage in John took place shortly after Jesus fed the 5000 (John 6:1).  After Jesus did a miracle and fed their bodies (their flesh, their natural and material hungers), they wanted to make Him their king, in an aim to displace the Roman authority that ruled over the Jews (John 6:15).  The Jews at that time viewed Messiah as one who would come and free them from the tyranny of the Romans; they thought He would be a &lt;i&gt;political&lt;/i&gt; authority rather than a &lt;i&gt;spiritual&lt;/i&gt; authority.  Jesus left them when He realized what it was they wanted to do because He did not come to setup an earthly kingdom -- that wasn't the point for His coming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this passage, the reference to "His disciples" is not to the 12 who would later be the apostles.  Jesus, to that time, had many disciples -- people who followed Him and wanted to learn what He was teaching.  When these disciples, and the 5000 men (and probably at least another 5000 women and children) finally caught up to Him again, Jesus recognized they were looking for the food He could provide to their bodies more than the food He could provide for their spirits.  He called them out on it in John 6:26-27 and He followed this with the "hard teaching" which Jesus gave, indicating that He was the bread of life and that He had come down from heaven and described His mission to humankind (eternal life).  These people didn't want to hear any of this, they simply wanted a free meal and someone who would provide for them materially.  So His words offended them and many deserted Him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this is what a lot of Christians in North America do today: we sell Jesus as a provider of free lunches ("He will bless you!" or "Your life will be so good!" and so on) and yet we never mention the &lt;i&gt;cost&lt;/i&gt; of what it is to follow Jesus.  It would serve some Christians well to pay attention to this... Jesus didn't sell Himself cheap, and He didn't chase after those who left.  Jesus laid it out for them straight, and they found the teaching hard because it wasn't what they were looking for and they didn't understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C.S. Lewis defines Christianity as this, in his book "Mere Christianity":&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Now the whole offer which Christianity makes is this: that we can, if we let God have His way, come to share in the life of Christ. If we do, we shall then be sharing a life which was begotten, not made, which always existed and always will exist. Christ is the Son of God. If we share in this kind of life we also shall be sons of God. We shall love the Father as He does and the Holy Ghost will arise in us. He came to this world and became a man in order to spread to other men the kind of life He has — by what I call "good infection." Every Christian is to become a little Christ. The whole purpose of becoming a Christian is simply nothing else.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While "Christian" does not necessarily mean "little Christ", I find it works quite well.  Truthfully, a number of commentators agree that "Christian" most likely started off as a derogatory term that would mean "follower of Christ" or "slave of Christ", both of which are not at all derogatory and really quite apt descriptions.  At any rate, our next few passages set out the call to be like (to imitate) Christ -- in a sense to become "little Christs".  In fact, Paul states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Therefore I urge you to &lt;b&gt;imitate me&lt;/b&gt;.”
(1 Corinthians 4:16 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“&lt;b&gt;Imitate me&lt;/b&gt;, as I also &lt;b&gt;imitate Christ&lt;/b&gt;.”
(1 Corinthians 11:1 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greek word &lt;i&gt;exakoloutheo&lt;/i&gt; means to follow out, to obey, or yield to.  Paul is urging the Corinthian church to imitate him as he imitates Christ, or to follow him as he follows Christ.  We as Christians are called to a live a life of imitation (of Christ), to be true disciples who see and do what our teacher shows us and asks of us.  Jesus is the standard that we set before us which is why it pains me (and should pain all true Christians) to see people who claim to bear the name of Christ acting in ways He never acted or say things that He would never say.  I suppose this could be because they are unfamiliar with what Jesus asks of us, or of how He would act in a given situation.  While all of this is clearly found in the Bible, too many people think the Bible unnecessary and don't bother to even crack open the book.  This is why Paul made the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Remind them of these things, charging them before God &lt;b&gt;not to fight about words&lt;/b&gt;; this is in no way profitable and leads to the ruin of the hearers. Be diligent to &lt;b&gt;present yourself &lt;i&gt;approved&lt;/i&gt; to God&lt;/b&gt;, a worker who doesn’t need to be ashamed, &lt;b&gt;correctly teaching&lt;/b&gt; the word of truth. But avoid irreverent, empty speech, for this will produce an even greater measure of godlessness. And their word will spread like gangrene; Hymenaeus and Philetus are among them. They have &lt;b&gt;deviated from the truth&lt;/b&gt;, saying that the resurrection has already taken place, and are overturning the faith of some. Nevertheless, God’s solid foundation stands firm, having this inscription: 
The Lord knows those who are His, and &lt;b&gt;Everyone who names the name of the Lord must turn away from unrighteousness&lt;/b&gt;.”
(2 Timothy 2:14–19 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The King James says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“&lt;b&gt;Study&lt;/b&gt; to shew thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing &lt;b&gt;the word of truth&lt;/b&gt;.”
(2 Timothy 2:15 KJV (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul is talking about studying the Word of God, the result of which is approval from God.  This is the only way that God can trust us to know His Will and it is the only way that we can imitate Christ: by reading the Bible to see what it is that we are to imitate.  Paul doesn't call us to just imitate random people; he calls us to imitate people who themselves are imitating Christ -- the end result is that we too will imitate Christ.  The other point here is that we need to study so as to prevent ourselves from being led astray and also preventing ourselves from leading &lt;i&gt;others&lt;/i&gt; astray.  There is a great responsibility and accountability on those who teach the Word of God, so I fear for those who profess to teach "the Word of God" and don't read or study it.  They are certainly not approved to God!  And they are those of whom Paul also speaks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“But I fear that, as the serpent &lt;b&gt;deceived&lt;/b&gt; Eve by his cunning, &lt;b&gt;your minds may be &lt;i&gt;seduced&lt;/i&gt; from a complete and pure devotion to Christ&lt;/b&gt;. For if a person comes and preaches &lt;b&gt;another Jesus&lt;/b&gt;, whom we did not preach, or you receive a &lt;b&gt;different spirit&lt;/b&gt;, which you had not received, or a &lt;b&gt;different gospel&lt;/b&gt;, which you had not accepted, you &lt;b&gt;put up with it&lt;/b&gt; splendidly!”
(2 Corinthians 11:3–4 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul clearly warns against false teachers who teach a different Jesus than the resurrected Jesus the apostles teach, or a different gospel than the gospel of Christ Jesus.  In an almost mocking/sarcastic tone he says "You put up with it &lt;i&gt;splendidly&lt;/i&gt;!", like they never even questioned it or compared it to what they were already taught and known.  Deceptive teaching is a very real danger -- it was then, and it still is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“I am amazed that you are &lt;b&gt;so quickly&lt;/b&gt; turning away from Him who called you by the grace of Christ and are &lt;b&gt;turning to a different gospel&lt;/b&gt;— not that there is another gospel, but there are some who are troubling you and want to &lt;b&gt;change the good news&lt;/b&gt; about the Messiah. &lt;b&gt;But even if we or an &lt;i&gt;angel from heaven&lt;/i&gt; should preach to you a gospel other than what we have preached to you, a curse be on him!&lt;/b&gt; As we have said before, I now say again: If anyone preaches to you a gospel contrary to what you received, a curse be on him!”
(Galatians 1:6–9 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is most disturbing about the above passage that Paul writes to the Galatians is that this very same thing is evident today.  We have major religions today that were delivered by "an angel from heaven": Mormonism and Islam.  In Mormonism, the angel "Moroni" delivered the plates of the Book of Mormon to Joseph Smith and while the Book of Mormon claims that the Gospel is true, it was corrupted (something which has not been proven scientifically despite many critical attempts to do so).  So while Mormons are to read the Bible, the Book of Mormon is considered superior, as Joseph Smith said: “I told the brethren that the Book of Mormon was the most correct of any book on earth, and the keystone of our religion, and a man would get nearer to God by abiding by its precepts, than by any other book.”&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" id="ref1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  This book was delivered by an angel and taught a different gospel!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the same is true of Islam, for Muhammad claimed that the Quran was delivered to him by the angel Gabriel&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn2" id="ref2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  The similarities between Islam and Mormonism are far more than just that they were delivered to their respective prophets by angels.  One other similarity is they both claim that the Bible (or more specifically the Gospel and the Torah) were, in their "uncorrupted" form, the Word of God and both the Quran and the Book of Mormon are further/final revelations of God to earth (see Surat '?li `Imr?n 3:3 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn3" id="ref3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the LDS web site topic on the Bible&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn4" id="ref4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, to wrap up, our final scripture which also talks about deceptive teachings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“If anyone teaches &lt;b&gt;other doctrine&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;does not agree&lt;/b&gt; with the sound teaching of our Lord Jesus Christ and with the &lt;b&gt;teaching that promotes godliness&lt;/b&gt;, he is conceited, understanding nothing, but has a sick interest in &lt;b&gt;disputes and arguments over words&lt;/b&gt;. From these come envy, quarreling, slander, evil suspicions, and constant disagreement among people whose minds are depraved and deprived of the truth, &lt;b&gt;who imagine that godliness is a way to material gain&lt;/b&gt;.”
(1 Timothy 6:3–5 HCSB (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the point of the Bible study was not to poke at other religions, they were used as examples as to why it is so important to study and know the Bible so that when these other doctrines and "gospels" come about, or even when preachers are preaching from the pulpit, Christians who have the Word of God written on their hearts will know the truth.  The hope is that we will recognize the lack of truth in others, but also recognize any lack of truth in our own words and actions which contradict the example Jesus set before us to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn1"&gt;1. &lt;a href="https://www.lds.org/scriptures/bofm/introduction"&gt;Book of Mormon: Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn2"&gt;2. &lt;a href="http://www.islamreligion.com/articles/2652/viewall/"&gt;The Story of the Quran (part 1 of 4): God's Final Revelation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn3"&gt;3. &lt;a href="http://quran.com/3/1-5"&gt;Surat '?li `Imr?n 3:1-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn4"&gt;4. &lt;a href="https://www.lds.org/topics/bible?lang=eng"&gt;LDS: Bible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category><category term="deception"></category></entry><entry><title>Using Romans 14 to improperly defend "Christian freedom"</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/using-romans-14-to-improperly-defend-christian-freedom" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-11-01T23:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2014-11-01T23:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2014-11-01:/blog/using-romans-14-to-improperly-defend-christian-freedom</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: I have not and will not participate in Halloween, and I personally do not believe that Christians should.  And while this posting talks about Halloween, it's not &lt;i&gt;about&lt;/i&gt; Halloween itself.  It's about misinterpreting scripture to suit your own desires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scripture in question is Romans 14:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Receive one …&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Full disclosure: I have not and will not participate in Halloween, and I personally do not believe that Christians should.  And while this posting talks about Halloween, it's not &lt;i&gt;about&lt;/i&gt; Halloween itself.  It's about misinterpreting scripture to suit your own desires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scripture in question is Romans 14:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Receive one who is weak in the faith, but not to disputes over doubtful things. For one believes he may eat all things, but he who is weak eats only vegetables. Let not him who eats despise him who does not eat, and let not him who does not eat judge him who eats; for God has received him. Who are you to judge another’s servant? To his own master he stands or falls. Indeed, he will be made to stand, for God is able to make him stand. 
One person esteems one day above another; another esteems every day alike. Let each be fully convinced in his own mind. He who observes the day, observes it to the Lord; and he who does not observe the day, to the Lord he does not observe it. He who eats, eats to the Lord, for he gives God thanks; and he who does not eat, to the Lord he does not eat, and gives God thanks. For none of us lives to himself, and no one dies to himself. For if we live, we live to the Lord; and if we die, we die to the Lord. Therefore, whether we live or die, we are the Lord’s. For to this end Christ died and rose and lived again, that He might be Lord of both the dead and the living. But why do you judge your brother? Or why do you show contempt for your brother? For we shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ. For it is written: “As I live, says the LORD, Every knee shall bow to Me, And every tongue shall confess to God.”
So then each of us shall give account of himself to God.”
(Romans 14:1–12 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This scripture was quoted in reference to a Christian handing out candy at Halloween, and why they believe it's acceptable.  To them, Halloween is not about celebrating darkness and witchcraft, it's about celebrating children and candy.  They are interpreting the scripture above to say "it's fine for me to participate in Halloween because I get to interact with my neighbours, as a Christian I can hand out the best candy with the biggest smile on my face and don't judge me because I choose to do so ("eat all things") whereas you refrain from participating in Halloween ("only eat vegetables") and I have the freedom in Christ do so because I'm doing it for the kids".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with that kind of thinking (paraphrased above) is that it doesn't account for the context of the scripture quoted.  Paul isn't talking about certain tastes in food ("I like beef and you like chicken -- don't judge me for liking beef!").  He's not even referring to the Jewish custom of not eating certain foods (such as pork).  Rather, he's talking about food sacrificed to idols.  The food in question was for sale on the market after it had been sacrificed to idols, and people would buy it from the market, knowing it's origin, take it home and eat it.  Some Christians thought that the very act of eating this food that had previously been sacrificed to idols meant they were partaking in idolatry (which is something that Christians would very much want to avoid).  For some Christians, this was a very real problem and they would not want to be seen as being partakers in the practice, and for others they looked at it for what it was: food to be eaten.  Give thanks to God for the food, and eat, regardless of where it came from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a definite problem with using this scripture to back the practice of Christians partaking in Halloween, and it's very much the "apples vs oranges" problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Primarily, you cannot compare the act of handing out candy in the same light as eating food sacrificed to idols.  They are two very different stages in a somewhat similar process.  Rather, you need to compare eating this kind of food to eating the candy procured through Halloween activities.  So the question of eating meat versus eating vegetables is the same as whether or not you should eat candy given to you that someone &lt;i&gt;else&lt;/i&gt; obtained while out trick-or-treating versus refusing to eat it (because of the association to Halloween).  In other words, if my neighbour comes over the day after Halloween and offers me some of the candy they collected the night before, I have to ask myself this: Does eating this candy make me a participator in the festivities or not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the act of handing out candy to children or taking your children out to collect candy from others can't be compared in the same way.  If we look at participation in Halloween as the sensitive issue today, then the sensitive issue when Romans 14 was written is the sacrificing to idols.  Perhaps it would be better to compare the &lt;i&gt;participation&lt;/i&gt; in either activity rather than the participation in one to the end result of the other.  Paul never compared the sacrificing of food to idols with the eating of this food.  For a Christian it would be a no-brainer: You don't sacrifice anything to idols.  So the &lt;i&gt;participation&lt;/i&gt; is not the focus because the answer is an unequivocal &lt;b&gt;NO&lt;/b&gt;.  Should that not be the same with this holiday originating in paganism and celebrated as the third most important day for Satanists today according to the Satanic Bible&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" id="ref1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of whether or not to partake of the treats obtained by &lt;i&gt;others&lt;/i&gt; who participated in Halloween should be the "freedom" that Christians need to think about and can use Romans 14 as a frame of reference.  You cannot use Romans 14 for the question of participation.  Instead, you should be using what Paul wrote to the Corinthians:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Do not be unequally yoked together with unbelievers. For what fellowship has righteousness with lawlessness? &lt;b&gt;And what communion has light with darkness? And what accord has Christ with Belial?&lt;/b&gt; Or what part has a believer with an unbeliever? And what agreement has the temple of God with idols? For you are the temple of the living God. As God has said: “I will dwell in them And walk among them. I will be their God, And they shall be My people.””
(2 Corinthians 6:14–16 NKJV (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this passage of scripture is the more appropriate question with some very definite answers.  There is nothing remotely Christian about Halloween and lame attempts to "Christianize" it to things like "Harvest Festival" are silly and were previously done -- in fact, the Catholic Church tried to Christianize Samhain to Halloween (or All Hallow's Eve) in the first place&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn2" id="ref2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Personally, I think they should have left well enough alone, like we should today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participating in Samhain&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn3" id="ref3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is something that, in my opinion, no Christian should be a part of.  In the same way that I don't think Christian missionaries in India celebrate Diwali, or Christians in Muslim countries celebrate Ramadan, I don't believe that cultural observances are an excuse to participate in something that is clearly not Christian.  And, to stem the comments of Easter and Christmas being "originally based in pagan holidays" I'd like to point out the obvious difference: Christmas is about celebrating the birth of our Lord Jesus Christ and Easter is about celebrating His death, burial and resurrection.  Regardless of what other holidays they may coincide with, there is an obvious meaning to the Christian that &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; based on Christ.  The use of Christmas trees may be a point of contention with some, but I believe that falls under the freedoms we have in Christ.  The significance of the holiday is something very important to a Christian to celebrate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also point out that those of other faiths such as Hindus and Muslims don't celebrate Christmas just because they live in Canada, so I think that "cultural observances" is a pretty weak excuse to participate in something that, unlike Christmas and Easter, has absolutely nothing to do with God nor glorifies God in the slightest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point of this article is not about Christians participating in Halloween.  As I stated before, I'm not one to judge.  I have many Christian friends who participate and I don't think any less of them.  I'm also not out to defend my right &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; to partake.  The point of this posting was to dispel the faulty logic behind using Romans 14 as a prop to say that it's ok.  All of us have to account for our thoughts and actions and only God is judge, not me, nor any other Christian.  But if you are going to participate, just do it without trying to build a defence on scriptures that contextually cannot be used.  For further in Romans 14 it states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“So then each of us shall give account of himself to God. Therefore let us not judge one another anymore, but rather resolve this, not to put a stumbling block or a cause to fall in our brother’s way. 
I know and am convinced by the Lord Jesus that there is nothing unclean of itself; but to him who considers anything to be unclean, to him it is unclean. Yet if your brother is grieved because of your food, you are no longer walking in love. Do not destroy with your food the one for whom Christ died.”
(Romans 14:12–15 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of us will give an account, and we should be considering others as well as ourselves.  Here Paul is stating that if a Christian brother or sister is grieved by your desire to eat food sacrificed to idols then don't do it and so become a stumbling block to them.  I say this to those who advertise the fact they are participating in Halloween and defending their "right" to participate.  Rather, if you want to participate in Halloween don't make a big deal of it -- just do it.  I don't make a big deal of the fact that I don't, yet to anyone who asks I will let them know my belief.  In the same way, why make a big deal of the fact that you do, and then go on to justify it as well?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it is up to you.  I don't at all believe that participating in Halloween affects salvation in any way or that it makes you a "worse Christian" than if you didn't.  However, as Christians we should really be thinking long and hard about what James wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“You adulterers! Don’t you realize that friendship with the world makes you an enemy of God? I say it again: If you want to be a friend of the world, you make yourself an enemy of God.”
(James 4:4 NLT)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn1"&gt;1. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanic_holidays"&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satanic_holidays&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn2"&gt;2. &lt;a href="http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/liturgicalyear/overviews/months/10_2.cfm"&gt;http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/liturgicalyear/overviews/months/10_2.cfm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn3"&gt;3. &lt;a href="http://inventors.about.com/od/sstartinventions/a/Samhain.htm"&gt;http://inventors.about.com/od/sstartinventions/a/Samhain.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Scripture quotes taken from the Holy Bible, New King James Version (NKJV) Copyright © 1982 by Thomas Nelson, Inc. and
the Holy Bible, New Living Translation (NLT) copyright© 1996, 2004, 2007 by Tyndale House Foundation. Used by permission of Tyndale House Publishers Inc., Carol Stream, Illinois 60188. All rights reserved.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category><category term="halloween"></category></entry><entry><title>Religion and Relationship</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/religion-and-relationship" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-26T15:19:00-06:00</published><updated>2014-10-26T15:19:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2014-10-26:/blog/religion-and-relationship</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whenever I hear (non-Christians) talk about Christianity it's always about "religion" and how they're "not into religion." When they make statements like this, I know that they have not heard the real gospel of Jesus Christ, nor do they understand what Christianity is all about.  When people talk about how …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whenever I hear (non-Christians) talk about Christianity it's always about "religion" and how they're "not into religion." When they make statements like this, I know that they have not heard the real gospel of Jesus Christ, nor do they understand what Christianity is all about.  When people talk about how they hate "organized religion" and then lump Christianity (in the broad sense) in the same category, they miss what Jesus said.  Don't miss the context and audience to whom Jesus is speaking to when He says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Brood of vipers! How can you, being evil, speak good things? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth speaks.”
(Matthew 12:34 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jesus also says to the religious leaders the following in this second passage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Serpents, brood of vipers! How can you escape the condemnation of hell?”
(Matthew 23:33 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly Jesus is condemning their "form of religion" in the same way God did with the Israelites in the Old Testament:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Therefore the Lord said: “Inasmuch as these people draw near with their mouths And honor Me with their lips, But have removed their hearts far from Me, And their fear toward Me is taught by the commandment of men,”
(Isaiah 29:13 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This scripture is also referenced by Jesus in Matthew 15.  The context is important in how Jesus quotes this, and in what He is trying to tell His disciples (those to whom the name "Christian" is later given):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Then the scribes and Pharisees who were from Jerusalem came to Jesus, saying, “Why do Your disciples transgress the tradition of the elders? For they do not wash their hands when they eat bread.”
He answered and said to them, “Why do you also transgress the commandment of God because of your tradition? For God commanded, saying, “Honor your father and your mother’; and, ‘He who curses father or mother, let him be put to death.’ But you say, “Whoever says to his father or mother, ‘Whatever profit you might have received from me is a gift to God”— then he need not honor his father or mother.’ Thus you have made the commandment of God of no effect by your tradition. Hypocrites! Well did Isaiah prophesy about you, saying: “These people draw near to Me with their mouth, And honor Me with their lips, But their heart is far from Me. And in vain they worship Me, Teaching as doctrines the commandments of men.’ ”
When He had called the multitude to Himself, He said to them, “Hear and understand: Not what goes into the mouth defiles a man; but what comes out of the mouth, this defiles a man.”
Then His disciples came and said to Him, “Do You know that the Pharisees were offended when they heard this saying?”
But He answered and said, “Every plant which My heavenly Father has not planted will be uprooted. Let them alone. They are blind leaders of the blind. And if the blind leads the blind, both will fall into a ditch.””
(Matthew 15:1–14 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pharisees and the scribes were the leaders of the Jewish religion of the day.  These are the people who took the Mosaic Law (the Laws of Moses) and turned them into the &lt;a href="http://www.jewfaq.org/613.htm"&gt;Mitzvot&lt;/a&gt;, a list of 613 commandments.  Keep in mind that God gave the people ten commandments on Mount Sinai (see Exodus 20 and Deuteronomy 5).  It was upon these ten commandments that the law was based (in Leviticus) when God gave specific direction to the people.  What most people don't realize is that God was giving laws for both spirituality/morality, as well as the "laws of the land" (similar to how we have built-in moral laws, yet we also have the laws of our justice systems, such as adhering to speed limits).  God was establishing His covenant people in terms of both their spiritual lives and their natural lives.  Given that the Israelites were a people bound in slavery and had no laws of their own, other than the laws of Egypt (their slave masters), God needed to establish the natural/judicial laws by which the &lt;i&gt;nation&lt;/i&gt; of Israel would adhere to -- similar to those that a King would establish for his people (and in the strictest sense, until the time of King Saul, Israel was a theocracy with God as their sole king).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what the Pharisees had done was take those judicial and spiritual laws to a whole new extreme (thus the 613 commandments) and this was the burden to the people.  Jesus took the ten commandments and distilled them down to two essential laws:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Then one of the scribes came, and having heard them reasoning together, perceiving that He had answered them well, asked Him, “Which is the first commandment of all?”
Jesus answered him, “The first of all the commandments is: ‘Hear, O Israel, the LORD our God, the LORD is one. And you shall love the LORD your God with all your heart, with all your soul, with all your mind, and with all your strength.’ This is the first commandment. And the second, like it, is this: “You shall love your neighbor as yourself.’ There is no other commandment greater than these.”
So the scribe said to Him, “Well said, Teacher. You have spoken the truth, for there is one God, and there is no other but He. And to love Him with all the heart, with all the understanding, with all the soul, and with all the strength, and to love one’s neighbor as oneself, is more than all the whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.”

Now when Jesus saw that he answered wisely, He said to him, “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” But after that no one dared question Him.”
(Mark 12:28–34 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Jesus was also referring to the burden of religion when He said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Come to Me, all you who labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest. Take My yoke upon you and learn from Me, for I am gentle and lowly in heart, and you will find rest for your souls. For My yoke is easy and My burden is light.””
(Matthew 11:28–30 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Christianity can be summed up in two commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Perfect love for God
&lt;li&gt; Proper love for man
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can ten commandments be expanded to 613, and then distilled down to two?  Being that I'm not Jewish, and that the Mitzvot is not in the Bible (and, likewise, considering Jesus' opinion concerning the weight of the burden the religious leaders were putting on people), I am only concerned with the ten commandments (see Exodus 20:2-17).  When you read the ten commandments it is easy to see that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt have no other gods before me (perfect love for God puts nothing before Him)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not make for yourself an idol (likewise, nothing comes before God)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not take name of the Lord thy God in vain (using the Lord's name as a curse is not showing Him love)
&lt;li&gt; Remember the Sabbath, to keep it holy (loving God means to take the time to develop a relationship with Him)
&lt;li&gt; Honor thy father and mother (proper love for people means honoring them, particularly those God has placed in authority over you, such as parents)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not kill (people don't kill people they love)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not commit adultery (this is the ultimate betrayal, or dishonor, of your spouse that you love)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not steal (people don't steal from people they love)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour (people don't lie to, or about, people they love)
&lt;li&gt; Thou shalt not covet what belongs to your neighbour (material possessions or spouse, it doesn't matter; those things that belong to other people belong to them)
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, rightfully, the ten commandments can be distilled down to two, as Jesus did.  When Jesus condemned the religious leaders, He spoke these words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;““Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you are like whitewashed tombs which indeed appear beautiful outwardly, but inside are full of dead men’s bones and all uncleanness. Even so you also outwardly appear righteous to men, but inside you are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness.”
(Matthew 23:27–28 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These words were spoken to them because they were concerned more with the &lt;i&gt;acts&lt;/i&gt; of men than with the &lt;i&gt;hearts&lt;/i&gt; of men.  To them, it was the works of righteousness, moreso than a humble heart, that God desired.  They put on masks (thus being called "hypocrites") so that they looked good on the outside, when on the inside they were more concerned with themselves and their positions of power than they were with actually obeying God.  It is for this reason that, when Saul did what looked good as opposed to what God commanded, that Samuel said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“So Samuel said: “Has the LORD as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices, As in obeying the voice of the LORD? Behold, to obey is better than sacrifice, And to heed than the fat of rams.”
(1 Samuel 15:22 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it's safe that, given all of the above, God is not interested in religion (as many define it today -- a set of rules you must live by), given how Jesus reacts to the Pharisees and religious leaders of His day.  Well known is John 3:16, which describes God's love for all humanity by sending His Son to be the sacrifice for our sins (&lt;i&gt;sin&lt;/i&gt; is defined as our disobedience and rebellion to God and His character, which are shown through His commands):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“For God so loved the world that He gave His only begotten Son, that whoever believes in Him should not perish but have everlasting life. For God did not send His Son into the world to condemn the world, but that the world through Him might be saved.”
(John 3:16–17 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“In this is love, not that we loved God, but that He loved us and sent His Son to be the propitiation for our sins.”
(1 John 4:10 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many times in the Bible, God is referred to as the Father... not just as the Father of Jesus, but our Father as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“If you then, being evil, know how to give good gifts to your children, how much more will &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;your Father&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; who is in heaven give good things to those who ask Him!”
(Matthew 7:11 NKJV (emphasis mine))&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the heart of God.  He is a Father to the fatherless (Psalm 68:5) and He is a Father to all.  The whole point of sending Jesus Christ to earth to die for us was to bridge the divide between God and man that our disobedience and rebellion caused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even more than this, consider Jesus -- He is a part of the triune God and the Father asks Him to come to earth to walk among us and teach us (to reveal the heart and will of God to us), and He is willing to do it.  He shows not only His obedience to God (with whom He's had relationship with for all eternity), but His love for us.  What other King would step off His throne to die for those who are meant to serve and worship Him?  What God would abandon divinity to become mortal flesh and then die, not for friends, not for anyone deserving, not for anyone who's earned it -- not &lt;i&gt;despite&lt;/i&gt; us but &lt;i&gt;for&lt;/i&gt; us?  Only Jesus Christ would do this, and He did it for &lt;i&gt;us&lt;/i&gt;, so that we could have relationship with God the Father, as He had for eternity.  In fact, before being arrested and ultimately sent to the cross, Jesus prayed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;““I do not pray for these alone, but also for those who will believe in Me through their word; that they all may be one, as You, Father, are in Me, and I in You; that they also may be one in Us, that the world may believe that You sent Me. And the glory which You gave Me I have given them, that they may be one just as We are one: I in them, and You in Me; that they may be made perfect in one, and that the world may know that You have sent Me, and have loved them as You have loved Me.”
(John 17:20–23 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The desire here is for the Father to have relationship with us in the same way that Jesus does.  When He says (paraphrased) "Father, You are in Me, and I am in You, and my prayer is for them to be one in Us and that the glory You gave to Me I have in turn given to them so that they can be united together as one in the same way that We are united together as One".  You cannot get any closer than to be united (which is to form as a unit or as a whole; a picture of this is the marriage covenant).  This is the closeness of the relationship Jesus desires with us -- so much so that in the Bible He is often referred to as the bridegroom and we (the church) as the bride.  Even in the Old Testament, God referred to the people of Israel as His wife (one such reference is Isaiah 54, another is the book of Hosea).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bring this to a close, it's clear to me that if Jesus condemned the forms/burdens of religion that the Pharisees practiced, then it is not something that we should be engaging in (this is not, however, a license to "do whatever you want" because, while Jesus condemned this, He also instructs us to live holy and righteous before God (or, to put it another way, He expects us to be obedient children to God the Father)).  Christianity was not meant to suck the life out of people making them do "stuff", nor was it meant to be a burden we carried alone.  John 10:10 says that Christ came to give us abundant life.  It is also clear that Jesus would not step down from His throne to give His life for people He didn't care about and that His death for us was the highest expression of love that He could give us, and that God even asking Him to do so was the highest expression of love that God could give (after all, would we give up our children for random strangers we cared nothing for and who hated us?).  Would you do that for anything less than the hope of a relationship with the ones you gave so much for, and an intense desire to have that relationship in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if God simply wanted our obedience, He could have made us with no free will or capacity for choice.  For God to have a true and genuine relationship with us, He had to create us with free will and offer us the choice: love Me or reject Me.  Just as children demonstrate love and honor to their parents by obeying them, we as children do the same to our heavenly Father.  If I &lt;i&gt;make&lt;/i&gt; my daughter do what I want and don't give her a choice, her "obedience" does not demonstrate love, it just shows good programming.  It is in the &lt;i&gt;choosing&lt;/i&gt; that we demonstrate love, so God had to create us with free will and the capacity for choice in order to have a genuine relationship with us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the word "religion" is not a dirty word as we have made it.  Almost 200 years ago &lt;a href="http://webstersdictionary1828.com/Home?word=Religion"&gt;Webster defined religion&lt;/a&gt; as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;1. &lt;i&gt;religion&lt;/i&gt; in its most comprehensive sense, includes a belief in the being and perfections of God, in the revelation of his will to man, in man's obligation to obey his commands, in a state of reward and punishment, and in man's accountableness to God; and also true godliness or piety of life, with the practice of all moral duties. It therefore comprehends theology, as a system of doctrines or principles, as well as practical piety; for the practice of moral duties without a belief in a divine lawgiver, and without reference to his will or commands, is not religion&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which I think is a pretty reasonable and accurate explanation for what religion is.  In other words, when we seek to define our position in relation to Almighty God we must ask ourselves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Who? God the Father, His Son Jesus Christ, the Holy Spirit, and man
&lt;li&gt; What? Obedience to His commands
&lt;li&gt; Where? Everywhere
&lt;li&gt; When? Now!
&lt;li&gt; Why? Relationship
&lt;li&gt; How? Religion
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="relationship"></category></entry><entry><title>Theological Terms</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/theological-terms" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-22T17:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2014-09-22T17:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2014-09-22:/blog/theological-terms</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I wrote about &lt;a href="/blog/christian-statements-of-faith"&gt;Christian Statements of Faith&lt;/a&gt;, which talks about the foundational pillars of Christianity -- those things that make Christianity what it is.  In this posting, I want to explain some theological terms that every Christian should know (sadly if you ask most Christians what these terms mean you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I wrote about &lt;a href="/blog/christian-statements-of-faith"&gt;Christian Statements of Faith&lt;/a&gt;, which talks about the foundational pillars of Christianity -- those things that make Christianity what it is.  In this posting, I want to explain some theological terms that every Christian should know (sadly if you ask most Christians what these terms mean you likely won't get a very good response). These terms and what they mean are most probably foreign to those who know nothing about Christianity (beyond what non-Christians describe, which is grossly inaccurate).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what, exactly, does "redemption" mean?  Or "justification"?  Or "sanctification"?  These are big words that are core to the belief of any Christian.  I am going to define them in brief and give a scripture reference for each; the interested reader can follow the links to definitions in Baker's Evangelical Dictionary of Biblical Theology which will explain these words in depth (looking at original Hebrew and Greek words with their meanings, further commentary and other scripture references -- I highly encourage taking the time to read it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These words, and the meaning behind them, are fundamental to understanding the Christian message and worldview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gospel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; means "Good News" or "Glad Tidings" and refers to the message of salvation and new life offered in and by Jesus Christ.  To the Christian, being cleansed of your sins and having the assurance of eternal life in the presence of God is indeed good news!&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" id="ref1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“AND NOW let me remind you [since it seems to have escaped you], brethren, of the Gospel (the glad tidings of salvation) which I proclaimed to you, which you welcomed and accepted and upon which your faith rests, And by which you are saved, if you hold fast and keep firmly what I preached to you, unless you believed at first without effect and all for nothing. For I passed on to you first of all what I also had received, that Christ (the Messiah, the Anointed One) died for our sins in accordance with [what] the Scriptures [foretold], That He was buried, that He arose on the third day as the Scriptures foretold, And [also] that He appeared to Cephas (Peter), then to the Twelve. Then later He showed Himself to more than five hundred brethren at one time, the majority of whom are still alive, but some have fallen asleep [in death]. Afterward He was seen by James, then by all the apostles (the special messengers), And last of all He appeared to me also, as to one prematurely and born dead [no better than an unperfected fetus among living men].”
(1 Corinthians 15:1–8 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salvation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; means "rescue, set free, deliverance, escape, wholeness, healing, and safety".  When we receive salvation, we are released from the bondage of sin and are no longer slaves to the sinful nature that each human being is born with.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn2" id="ref2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“For God so greatly loved and dearly prized the world that He [even] gave up His only begotten (unique) Son, so that whoever believes in (trusts in, clings to, relies on) Him shall not perish (come to destruction, be lost) but have eternal (everlasting) life. For God did not send the Son into the world in order to judge (to reject, to condemn, to pass sentence on) the world, but that the world might find salvation and be made safe and sound through Him.”
(John 3:16–17 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repentance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; means a complete change of direction in a person's life (for example, you are travelling north, then you turn around and travel south in the opposite direction).  It is a complete change of the mind, will and emotions away from sin and towards God.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn3" id="ref3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“Let the wicked forsake his way and the unrighteous man his thoughts; and let him return to the Lord, and He will have love, pity, and mercy for him, and to our God, for He will multiply to him His abundant pardon.”
(Isaiah 55:7 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Redemption&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; is the means by which salvation is achieved, by the payment of a ransom.  It literally means "to buy" and signifies the act of purchase in the market (in particular the slave market).  For a Christian, we are redeemed, or have received redemption, from being slaves to sin and through the purchase of ourselves with the precious blood of Jesus Christ on the cross.  He paid &lt;i&gt;our&lt;/i&gt; debt to God for &lt;i&gt;our&lt;/i&gt; sins on &lt;i&gt;our&lt;/i&gt; behalf.  The death we deserved as sinners before a Holy and Righteous God, Jesus took upon Himself and died in our place.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn4" id="ref4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“In Whom we have our redemption through His blood, [which means] the forgiveness of our sins.”
(Colossians 1:14 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atonement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; is the term used to sum up the entire saving work of Christ, the offering of a redemptive sacrifice for the sin of man.  Atonement is God's action -- His work, not man's.  Man cannot provide atonement for sin, only God can.  Jesus Christ died the death that every person on the planet deserved and through this act of complete surrender, God's divine justice was satisfied and the wrath of God against sin was appeased.  This satisfaction concerning sin is called &lt;em&gt;propitiation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn5" id="ref5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“He went once for all into the [Holy of] Holies [of heaven], not by virtue of the blood of goats and calves [by which to make reconciliation between God and man], but His own blood, having found and secured a complete redemption (an everlasting release for us). For if [the mere] sprinkling of unholy and defiled persons with blood of goats and bulls and with the ashes of a burnt heifer is sufficient for the purification of the body, How much more surely shall the blood of Christ, Who by virtue of [His] eternal Spirit [His own preexistent divine personality] has offered Himself as an unblemished sacrifice to God, purify our consciences from dead works and lifeless observances to serve the [ever] living God?”
(Hebrews 9:12–14 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Justified&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; means "to declare or pronounce righteous" (as my pastor likes to say, "just as if I'd never sinned").  Justification is the act of God removing the guilt, condemnation, and the penalty of sin from the believer and placing His own standard of righteousness on them.  This is not something that man can obtain on his own.  It's similar to being acquitted of a crime, but goes much further because as sinners we are guilty -- in other words, we are guilty and deserve the penalty of sin, but God not only doesn't punish us for it, He removes the stain of it from us so completely that it's as if it was never there.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn6" id="ref6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“[And He did it in order] that we might be justified by His grace (by His favor, wholly undeserved), [that we might be acknowledged and counted as conformed to the divine will in purpose, thought, and action], and that we might become heirs of eternal life according to [our] hope.”
(Titus 3:7 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Faith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, in the theological context, means "firm persuasion, belief, conviction, reliance, and complete trust in God alone for salvation".  I like how Noah Webster's American Dictionary of the English Language (1828) describes it (one of the twelve definitions it has): "&lt;i&gt;3. In theology, the assent of the mind or understanding to the truth of what God has revealed.  Simple belief of the scriptures, of the being and perfections of God, and of the existence, character and doctrines of Christ, founded on the testimony of the sacred writers, is called historical or speculative faith; a faith little distinguished from the belief of the existence and achievements of Alexander or of Cesar.&lt;/i&gt;"&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn7" id="ref7"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“But without faith it is impossible to please and be satisfactory to Him. For whoever would come near to God must [necessarily] believe that God exists and that He is the rewarder of those who earnestly and diligently seek Him [out].”
(Hebrews 11:6 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grace&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; is the undeserved kindness of God or the "unmerited favour" of God.  It is favour that cannot be purchased, gained or earned -- it is 100% the gift of God, and can only be given by God.  This kindness of God came to the world in the form of Jesus Christ who died for us to make us righteous before God.  And as a gift, it can be accepted or rejected.  The Christian accepts this gift of God, the non-Christian rejects it.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn8" id="ref8"&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“For it is by free grace (God’s unmerited favor) that you are saved (delivered from judgment and made partakers of Christ’s salvation) through [your] faith. And this [salvation] is not of yourselves [of your own doing, it came not through your own striving], but it is the gift of God; Not because of works [not the fulfillment of the Law’s demands], lest any man should boast. [It is not the result of what anyone can possibly do, so no one can pride himself in it or take glory to himself.]”
(Ephesians 2:8–9 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adoption&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; means to be placed as a son or daughter into a family, as an actual member of the family with all of the responsibilities and benefits of the family being adopted into.  When God says that we have been adopted as sons, it is not to be a part of the family of God as second-class citizens but as heirs to all of the promises of God.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn9" id="ref9"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“To purchase the freedom of (to ransom, to redeem, to atone for) those who were subject to the Law, that we might be adopted and have sonship conferred upon us [and be recognized as God’s sons]. And because you [really] are [His] sons, God has sent the [Holy] Spirit of His Son into our hearts, crying, Abba (Father)! Father! Therefore, you are no longer a slave (bond servant) but a son; and if a son, then [it follows that you are] an heir by the aid of God, through Christ.”
(Galatians 4:5–7 AMP)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sanctification&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt; means "to make holy" or "holiness".  This is where we get the word "saint" from ("saint" is &lt;em&gt;hagios&lt;/em&gt; in Greek, meaning "a sanctified one", from the Greek &lt;em&gt;hagiasmos&lt;/em&gt; or "holiness", which is the Greek word translated "sanctification").  Another way to look at this is that to be sanctified, or holy, is when a person lives according to God's design and purpose.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn10" id="ref10"&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;“to open their eyes, in order to turn them from darkness to light, and from the power of Satan to God, that they may receive forgiveness of sins and an inheritance among those who are sanctified by faith in Me.’”
(Acts 26:18 NKJV)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, many other terms that could be defined but I think that these are the most important "pillars" of what it means to be a Christian.  The meanings of these words are at the heart of Christian "language" and describe what we believe and show their use and context.  They also illustrate the Christian worldview, to some degree, because they help to provide clarity to how we view the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every person has their own worldview -- the lens through which they view the world.  Whether you are Christian, Atheist, Muslim, Hindu, whatever... you have a worldview and there are certain words used to describe that worldview.  In the Christian context, these words are supremely important because they convey certain imagery in a powerful way.  A Christian shouldn’t be tossing these words around without knowing what they mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, when a Christian says "I have been redeemed" or a song's lyrics talk about redemption, we should know what we are saying or singing.  Without a full understanding of the word, it's just words.  As with any words, it's the meaning behind them that give them depth, that give them purpose.  Saying "I have been redeemed" means nothing if you don't know that it paints a picture of our state as slaves to sin, as hopeless captives, without any possibility of rescue in and of ourselves, but that it is only by the price Jesus paid on the cross that we have been taken from the pit of slavery, never to look back.  We have been bought with a price, the blood of Jesus on the cross, so saying "I have been redeemed" should bring to mind the work of Jesus on the cross, the steep price He paid in the suffering, pain, and torture He endured for my sake and for yours.  Knowing the state we were in, and the high price paid, should bring us to deep gratitude and thankfulness, knowing that there is no rescue, no &lt;i&gt;thing&lt;/i&gt;, that we could ever possibly do to purchase our own freedom or place us in right standing before an infinite, holy, and righteous God.  The picture behind the simple statement "I have been redeemed" is rich and potent, yet without the understanding of the word itself, it is minimized to nothing more than a "religious catch-phrase" which robs us of the precious meaning and majesty behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn1"&gt;1. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/gospel.html"&gt;Gospel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn2"&gt;2. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/salvation.html"&gt;Salvation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn3"&gt;3. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/repentance.html"&gt;Repentance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn4"&gt;4. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/redeem-redemption.html"&gt;Redemption, Redeem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn5"&gt;5. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/atonement.html"&gt;Atonement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn6"&gt;6. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/justification.html"&gt;Justified, Justification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn7"&gt;7. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/faith.html"&gt;Faith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn8"&gt;8. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/grace.html"&gt;Grace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn9"&gt;9. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/adoption.html"&gt;Adoption&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn10"&gt;10. Defined: &lt;a href="http://www.biblestudytools.com/dictionaries/bakers-evangelical-dictionary/sanctification.html"&gt;Sanctification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Scripture quotes taken from the Amplified Bible (AMP) copyright © 1954, 1958, 1962, 1964, 1965, 1987 by The Lockman Foundation, and The Holy Bible, New King James Version (NKJV) Copyright © 1982 by Thomas Nelson, Inc.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category><category term="faith"></category><category term="theology"></category></entry><entry><title>Christian Statements of Faith</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/christian-statements-of-faith" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-11T22:35:00-06:00</published><updated>2014-09-11T22:35:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2014-09-11:/blog/christian-statements-of-faith</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the course of my studies I've come to realize that a lot of people have no idea what Christianity really means -- even people who profess to be Christian really don't understand what it means, and this is the real disappointment as the North American church has done a fantastic …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the course of my studies I've come to realize that a lot of people have no idea what Christianity really means -- even people who profess to be Christian really don't understand what it means, and this is the real disappointment as the North American church has done a fantastic job of conforming the gospel to our culture when we should be aiming to conform our culture to the gospel (in other words, if we try to conform Truth, we end up with a twisted view of the truth or an outright lie).  In a later posting I'll tackle the issue of truth (what it is and why it matters); suffice it to say for now I believe that truth is not subjective as relativism claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin to understand the origin of Christianity, you need to understand the orthodoxy of Christianity (the theories, doctrines, and practices that defined Christianity in the early church and are the pillars of Christian theology today).  These statements or creeds are inviolate -- they are the foundations of Christianity and without them you may have something that &lt;em&gt;resembles&lt;/em&gt; Christianity, but really &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; Christianity.  There are two statements of faith that define Christianity: the Apostles' Creed and the Nicene Creed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Apostles' Creed&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
1. I believe in God the Father almighty, creator of heaven and earth.
2. I believe in Jesus Christ, his only Son, our Lord.
3. He was conceived by the power of the Holy Spirit and born of the Virgin Mary.
4. Under Pontius Pilate, He was crucified, died, and was buried.
5. He descended to the dead. On the third day he rose again.
6. He ascended into heaven and is seated at the right hand of the Father.
7. He will come again to judge the living and the dead.
8. I believe in the Holy Spirit,
9. the holy catholic Church, the communion of saints,
10. the forgiveness of sins,
11. the resurrection of the body,
12. and the life everlasting.
Amen.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I'm not catholic and this doesn't mean "catholic church" in the sense that we understand it today (not to be confused with the "Catholic Church" as an organized religion today).  It comes from the Greek words &lt;em&gt;kata&lt;/em&gt; (with respect to) and &lt;em&gt;holos&lt;/em&gt; (whole) so the meaning of "catholic" in this statement is the universal (&lt;em&gt;katholikos&lt;/em&gt;) church (or, to put it into our language today, "the holy world-wide united christian church" (again, not to be confused with the "United Church" as an organized religion today)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Nicene Creed&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
We believe in one God, the Father Almighty, maker of heaven and earth, and of all things visible and invisible.

And in one Lord Jesus Christ, the only begotten Son of God, begotten of his Father before all worlds, God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God, begotten, not made, being of one substance with the Father; by whom all things were made; who for us and for our salvation came down from heaven, and was incarnate by the Holy Spirit of the Virgin Mary, and was made man; and was crucified also for us under Pontius Pilate; he suffered and was buried; and the third day he rose again according to the Scriptures, and ascended into heaven, and is seated at the right hand of the Father; and he shall come again, with glory, to judge both the living and the dead; whose kingdom shall have no end.

And I believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, and giver of life, who proceeds from the Father and the Son; who with the Father and the Son together is worshipped and glorified; who spoke by the prophets; and we believe in the one holy catholic and apostolic church; we acknowledge one baptism for the forgiveness of sins; and we look for the resurrection of the dead, and the life of the world to come.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the Nicene Creed was initially written in 325 AD at the first council of Nicea, and expanded (and slightly re-arranged) at the first council of Constantinople in 381 AD.  This creed was considered the Symbol of Faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these creeds are foundational to Christianity.  To take away or change any of these statements removes the foundational material of the faith and fundamentally changes the faith to something that is like Christianity, but is not, in fact, Christianity.  For instance, Jehovah's Witnesses, despite having a similar Bible and similar beliefs, are not Christian -- they deny the triune nature of God and deny that Jesus is God, both of which are foundational truths to the Christian belief.  Therefore a Jehovah's Witness cannot (and will not) claim to be Christian, because the foundations of the Jehovah's Witness faith are drastically and fundamentally different (not meaning to pick on Jehovah's Witnesses here, but they are probably the closest almost-but-definitely-not-Christian faith I can think of).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to reiterate what I noted above about the "catholic church" because I think it's very important to note, particularly for readers that are not Christian and don't understand the denominational differences that various churches have.  I like the way that Charles Colson and Harold Fickett explain it in their book "The Faith"&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href="#fn1" id="ref1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Church is &lt;i&gt;one&lt;/i&gt; because all true Christians, while we participate in different confessing congregations, are part of one body.  That body is &lt;i&gt;holy&lt;/i&gt; because its essential nature is found in Christ.  The Church is &lt;i&gt;catholic&lt;/i&gt; because it is universal, which is what &lt;i&gt;catholic&lt;/i&gt; means -- the Church is open to everyone.  Finally, the Church is &lt;i&gt;apostolic&lt;/i&gt;, which means that its teachings are those of the apostles.  We have not invented a religion.  We are part of the faith God revealed.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and perhaps most important to me, these are &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; statements of faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;sup id="fn1"&gt;1. Charles W. Colson, Harold Fickett, &lt;i&gt;The Faith&lt;/i&gt; (Grand Rapids, Michigan: Zondervan, 2008), 157-158.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category><category term="faith"></category></entry><entry><title>Christianity</title><link href="https://annvix.com/blog/christianity" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-09-09T17:59:00-06:00</published><updated>2014-09-09T17:59:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Vincent Danen</name></author><id>tag:annvix.com,2014-09-09:/blog/christianity</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've had to rearrange the layout of the blog to accommodate some new postings that will be showing up here in the future.  As an aside, my apologies to those who visit and see that I have been sadly lacking in any kind of content on the site.  I will …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've had to rearrange the layout of the blog to accommodate some new postings that will be showing up here in the future.  As an aside, my apologies to those who visit and see that I have been sadly lacking in any kind of content on the site.  I will be making a distinct effort to rectify this moving forward, although perhaps not in the way that most might expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since May I have been engaging in theological studies through my church's off-campus theology program (&lt;a href="http://christcity.com/training/CTI"&gt;Christcity Theological Institute&lt;/a&gt; for anyone curious).  The material we have been going through has been exceptional and between a crazy amount of work and my studies I've not had much time for posting random things.  I haven't had time to do extra-curricular mucking around with random computer things like I used to, so there isn't as much to write about as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as I've gone through these theological materials (and others), I realize I do have something worth writing about, but it stands apart from the typical content that has been published here for years.  To that end, I opted to keep my thoughts and writings about Christianity and my faith from the front page of the site -- purely to keep the tech focus on the site.  Since I don't feel like maintaining a second blog and don't want to come across as a "Bible thumper" or have anyone feel like I'm attempting to shove my faith down their throat, I've intentionally set these pieces out of "simple sight".  They are perfectly visible in all respects beyond not being on the front page, as I have a feeling these posts may be quite lengthy.  They will be syndicated to my Facebook and Google+ pages, as well as my Twitter feed.  Anyone who haunts those will find that these posts are no real surprise given what I tend to tweet/post (again, rather infrequently as I don't have much time for social media these days either).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please understand that this is by no means an attempt to "hide my faith" as, if that were the aim, I could simply not post these things to begin with.  Also understand that comments have always been moderated on this site, and will continue to be, so that isn't new.  I am more than happy for questions or reasonable comments, but will likely ignore flames or other questionable comments -- I'm not here to pick fights and won't respond to any in kind.  You're free to believe what you like, and you're free to read what you like (and the same holds true for myself).  If you don't like what I write, simply don't read it.  If you're curious or have genuine questions, I will certainly welcome them and try to answer as best I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a journey for understanding.  I have always been a Christian (although not always a very good one!) and I have always had a firmness to my faith, but these studies answer more questions than I had thought to ask (and I will admit that, growing up, this was the adoption of my parents' faith; this is now beyond the shadow of a doubt &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; faith).  However, as I study, Christianity makes sense and in the light of other religions and philosophies in the world, it makes the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; sense.  Future postings will have examples of what I mean by this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that I am not a "religious person" and don't believe in following rules for their own sake.  Yes, the orthodoxy of Christianity is religious, in that there is a set of doctrines and beliefs but that is merely the shape of the box.  What is inside the box is vastly different, and is not defined by strict adherence to rules/regulations/laws.  Yes, these things exist and they do so for a purpose, but the fundamental premise and ideology behind the Bible is simple: it's a love story about relationships.  Relationship with God the Father, Jesus the Son, and the Holy Spirit.  Relationships with each other.  I believe that "religion" and the same adherence to rules/regulations/laws are things that have contributed to atrocities committed in the past in the name of God, but were not done in the spirit of what the Bible teaches and so can no more be attributed to God than cars running children over can be attributed to automobile manufacturers, or that murderers can be attributed to law makers.  I will get more into all of this in later posts, however.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, for those to whom this may offend: I'm not sorry, it's not on the frontpage, and just don't read it if you don't like it or disagree with it.  Don't feel like you need to post to "convert" me as my aim in posting is not to "convert" you.  To those who want to read, I encourage you to use the RSS feed to be made aware of when new postings are out.  For those concerned these will hit Planet Fedora, don't worry about it.  They won't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“I'm convinced that most men don't know what they believe, rather, they only know what they wish to believe. How many people blame God for man's atrocities, but wouldn't dream of imprisoning a mother for her son's crime?” 
? Criss Jami
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my way of knowing not only what I believe, but &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I believe it.  And not just "knowing" but &lt;em&gt;knowing&lt;/em&gt;.  Why would I want to believe in something that is false or that, when you dig past the surface, doesn't make sense?  It concerns me how many people condemn Christianity but know nothing about it, or those who believe in it but have never asked themselves why they do.  Similarly, people shouldn't condemn the Muslim faith without bothering to know anything more than what media presents, while at the same time Muslims should be questioning and looking into their own faith (although this is admittedly difficult due to Sharia Law -- this, in itself, should be causing them to question!).  Even many Darwinists (or Naturalists, or Athiests) never bother to understand the views they implicitly oppose and, if I may be so bold, often don't look logically at their own worldview and philosophy to know what it is they are even professing to believe in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my way of articulating, both to myself and to others who care to take the same journey, or are already on it, why it is that I believe what I believe and that it isn't some mindless, blind devotion to a dead religion, but a logical and reasonable walk of faith.  I'm not concerned about taking this journey -- after all, if I'm wrong then I want, and need, to know it.  It's not enough for me to be a "good person" or to be a "pew warmer" on a Sunday, get some warm fuzzies and feel good about myself and then be, as James 1:22 says, merely a hearer of the word and not a doer of the word and in the end, simply deceiving myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every Christian should be unafraid to take an honest look at the faith, we are in fact instructed to study and learn and understand the Bible and our faith:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Study and be eager and do your utmost to present yourself to God approved (tested by trial), a workman who has no cause to be ashamed, correctly analyzing and accurately dividing [rightly handling and skillfully teaching] the Word of Truth.”
(2 Timothy 2:15 AMP)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
“But in your hearts revere Christ as Lord. Always be prepared to give an answer to everyone who asks you to give the reason for the hope that you have. But do this with gentleness and respect, keeping a clear conscience, so that those who speak maliciously against your good behavior in Christ may be ashamed of their slander.”
(1 Peter 3:15–16 TNIV)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you give an answer for something you do not understand?  As far as I am concerned, these two scriptures indicate that God wants us to know what we believe and why we believe it.  Why?  So that, if we fully understand, we will live our lives according to that understanding -- not simply paying lip-service to a philosophy or good idea, but actually living our lives in such a way that our belief is seen in how we act, not just in what we say.  A &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; belief is something that does not change to suit us.  We change to suit it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, as Christians, are called to be agents of change to the world.  How can we possibly change anything if we don't &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; believe that what we believe is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; real?*  Just look around and you'll see how poorly we preach the true gospel of Jesus Christ in North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;* (Yes, this statement is taken from the Truth Project because I couldn't possibly articulate it better)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="christianity"></category><category term="faith"></category></entry></feed>